Okay, today's דף daf is דף ו daf vav גיטין, Gittin, we're
in a new מסכת masechet and we pick up at the bottom
of ה heh עמוד amud ב. bet. We've just gone through the
debate of רבה Rabbah and רבא Rava whether the reason for בפני
נכתב ובפני נחתם bifani nechtav u'bifani nechtam is because of the issue
of לשמה lishmah to ensure that the הלכות halachot and לשמה lishmah
in particular was done properly, which is רבה's Rabbah position, which focuses
on the words בפני נכתב, bifani nechtav, the כתיבה, ktivah, whereas רבא's
Rava position is that it has to be it's a way of
validating the signatures so that the husband cannot challenge that it was
a forgery and that's sort of reflected more in the word בפני
נחתם, bifani nechtam, it was signed. And in the end, the גמרא
Gemara says that רבה Rabbah actually is concerned, also holds of רבא's
Rava position, that it's both about לשמה lishmah and about validating and
רבא Rava only is concerned about validating. And the גמרא Gemara has
worked through both trying to bring proofs from the various parts of
the משנה Mishnah and spell out what the different implications
of it all is and how that might play out in the
different circumstances, whether you give the גט get before two or before
three,
whether if you didn't say בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם bifani nechtav u'bifani
nechtam you can just do a validation and in the end the
גמרא Gemara actually said that רבה Rabbah wound up being almost identical
to רבא Rava because there was also a period where in מדינת
הים medinat hayam they learned the laws of לשמה lishmah so really
the need of the לשמה lishmah element even for רבה Rabbah is
really more of a לכתחילה. lechatchila.
Okay, so that was a quick summary of everything we've done until
now and now we pick up on ה heh עמוד amud ב
bet with the following.
בר הדיא Bar Hadaya so it's one, two, three, four, five, six,
seven lines from the bottom, middle of the line. בר הדיא בעי
לאתויי גיטא. Bar Hadaya ba'ei le'atuye gita. בר הדיא Bar Hadaya wanted
to bring a גט. get.
אתא לקמיה דרבי אחי, ata lekamei de'Rabbi Achi, came in front of
רבי אחי Rabbi Achi in the city in which they were seeing
it. He was going to be sent to bring the גט get
and he now had to be present while it was being written
so he could say בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם. bifani nechtav u'bifani nechtam.
דעביד
ממנא אגיטא, de'avid mumna agita, רבי אחי Rabbi Achi was the one
appointed overseeing making sure that the גיטין gittin were being done properly
and as רש"י Rashi points out if you look at רש"י Rashi
here, last רש"י Rashi on the page, דקיימא לן כל שאינו יודע
בטיב גיטין וקידושין לא יהא לו עסק עמהן. de'kaima lan kol she'eino
yode'a betiv gittin ve'kiddushin lo yehei lo esek imahen. If you don't
know fully, you're completely fluent in the laws of גיטין Gittin and
קידושין Kiddushin you should have no dealings with them, stay a mile
away. This is about personal status and it's very complicated and a
lot of requirements, so you really need somebody who knows what they
are doing to be authorized.
והוו ממנו גברא רבה למיחזי היכי עביד ve'havei mimenu gavra raba lere'ei
heichi avid and therefore they would always point a person of real
authority in order to supervise. So he came in front of רבי
אחי. Rabbi Achi. אתא לקמיה דרבי אחי דהוה ממנא אגיטא. ata lekamei
de'Rabbi Achi de'hava mumna agita. אמר ליה, amar lei, he said, רבי
אחי Rabbi Achi said to him: צריך את למעמד על כל אות
ואות. tzarich at l'amod al kol ot ve'ot. You have to be
present as every single letter is being written from the beginning of
the גט get till the final signature because you have to say
בפני נכתב, bifani nechtav, it was written, בפני נחתם. bifani nechtam. So
the question here is: what does it mean in my presence? How
present do you have to be when this is being done? אזל
לקמיה דרבי אמי ורבי אסי, azal lekamei de'Rabbi Ammi ve'Rabbi Assi, he
came in front of רבי אמי Rabbi Ammi and רבי אסי. Rabbi
Assi. אמרי ליה, amri lei, they said to him, לא צריכת, lo
tzarichat, no, that seemed a little excessive to him and they said
no, actually you don't have to. You know, maybe this happens sometimes
when you have supervision, like you have כשרות kashrut industries, they create
a standard that is actually much higher than is absolutely required.
So maybe that was this principle of רבי אחי Rabbi Achi or
maybe they actually just debated it. Anyway, they said that was not
necessary. וכי תימא אביד לחומרא, ve'chi teima avid lechumra, but you said
look, you know what, that's the higher standard that רבי אחי Rabbi
Achi set, maybe I should do it just to be really really
careful so I can say בפני נכתב bifani nechtav you know about
every letter. נמצא אתה מוציא לעז על גיטין הראשונים. nimtza ata motzi
la'az al gittin harishonim. No, then you are going to spread ill
repute against the early גיטין gittin because people are going to hear
that you were מקפיד makpid you know to make sure that you
supervised every single letter and you were present as every letter was
being written, people will then start to question the validity of the
earlier גיטין gittin and this is a very important principle about you
know the costs that come with חומרות chumras and being you know
stringent more than is necessary. Oh, who does it hurt? I'm just
be מחמיר machmir and then what type of what does it impute
about people that practice otherwise or about past practice. Okay.
רבה בר בר חנה אייתי גיטא פלגא איכתב קמיה פלגא לא איכתב
קמיה. Rabbah bar bar Chana ayiti gita palga ichtav kamey palga lo
ichtav kamey. He brought a גט, get, half was written in his
presence, half not.
It doesn't say which half. אתא לקמיה דרבי אלעזר. ata lekamei de'Rabbi
Elazar. אמר ליה amar lei אפילו לא כתב בו אלא שיטה אחת
לשמה שוב אינו צריך. afilu lo katav bo ela shita achat lishmah
shuv eino tzarich.
Even if only one שיטה, shita, one line was written לשמה, lishmah,
that's sufficient. Now, why does one line suffice?
Also notice the לשמה. lishmah. This is sort of addressing a רבה
Rabbah point because this is about the בפני נכתב. bifani nechtav. We're
not talking about what it means to be signed in front of
you, but this is just the part to be written in front
of you.
And now you could understand that since you know there's an assumption
now that basically everybody already knows the הלכה, halacha, it's only a
לכתחילה lechatchila even in the time when there was a concern of
לשמה, lishmah, if you heard that the סופר sofer was being מקפיד
makpid that
he
meaning you heard they said I'm doing this for the sake of
the husband and for the sake of the wife, you know, and
so if you heard that at one line, you could assume that
they obviously know the הלכה halakha and they're doing it about everything.
I would think that that's פשט. pshat. תוספות Tosafot if you look
says the following: אפילו לא כתב אלא שיטה אחת, afilu lo kasav
ela shita achas, פירוש שלא ראה אלא שיטה ראשונה, pirush shelo ra'ah
ela shita rishona, דמסתמא סיים לשמה. demis'tama siyeim lishmah. You saw the
beginning, you're going to assume the end. That to me seems a
little bit not פשט pshat of the גמרא. Gemara. It says half,
doesn't say which half, it says any one line, and seems that
that should be sufficient given what the level of concern of לשמה
lishmah is. Anyway, that is the הלכה halakha about the כתיבה. ksiva.
We're not yet addressing the חתימה. chasima. If the חתימה chasima has
to stand in for, you know, being able to for a type
of קיום שטרות, kiyum shtaros, a validation of signatures, you would think
you actually have to see the people sign it themselves. Okay, רב
אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, רב אשי Rav Ashi says, not you
don't it's even less than one line. אפילו כאן קולמוסא וכאן מגילתא,
afilu kan kulmusa vekan megilta, even if you just hear the fixing
of the of the quill and the fixing of the קלף, klaf,
you know, that is sufficient. רש״י Rashi has a different גרסא girsa
of קל קולמוסא, kal kulmusa, the קול. kol. Let's look at רש״י:
Rashi: אפילו שמע תיקון הקולמוס והקלף, afilu shama tikun hakulmus vehaklaf, וכן
תיקון, vechen tikun, the fixing of it like when they're, you know,
scraping it. שמע כשתיקנו לשמה, shama k'shetiknu lishmah, that you're doing it
לשמה. lishmah. So they're even sort of, you know, cutting, now obviously
you don't have to make a quill לשמה, lishmah, but if you're
hearing them as they're doing that and saying like we're going to
be doing this for the sake of the woman and so on
and you hear some context where they're clearly concerned about the לשמה,
lishmah, that's enough to say it was written in front of me,
very loose use of the word written, not in I mean, you
know, and in front, you only heard it, you didn't see it,
and you didn't even actually see it, it wasn't even during the
time of the writing. תניא כוותיה דרב אשי, Tanya kevasei deRav Ashi,
and taught similar to Rav Ashi. המביא גט ממדינת הים, Hamavi get
mimdinas hayam, אפילו הוא בבית והסופר בעליה, afilu hu babayis vehasofer ba'aliya,
if you're bringing a גט get ממדינת הים, mimdinas hayam, even if
you're in the house and the סופר sofer was when it was
being written and the סופר sofer was up on the second story.
הוא בעליה והסופר בבית, Hu ba'aliya vehasofer babayis, or the reverse. אפילו
נכנס ויוצא כל היום כולו, afilu nichnas veyotzei kol hayom kulo, even
if you're going in and out the whole day as the סופר
sofer writing it, כשר. kasher. Okay, it's kosher. Now הוא בבית והסופר
בעליה הלא לא חזי ליה, hu babayis vehasofer ba'aliya halo lo chazi
lei, now the גמרא Gemara says one minute, let's understand how do
you what does that mean if you're downstairs and he's upstairs? You
have no you're not seeing it and you're not even sort of
like aware that it's being written. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא
לאו דשמע כאן קולמוסא וכאן מגילתא, ela lav d'shama kan kulmusa vekan
megilta, it must mean some sense you are aware and you're in
the presence without seeing it. בפני, Bifnai, in my presence in the
sense that, you know, I could hear him doing it upstairs. Now
I will also point out by the way that this גמרא Gemara
does not say לשמה. lishmah. Before it said לשמה. lishmah. And if
you remember according to רבה, Rabbah, the only need to say בפני
נכתב bifnei nichtav was to make it sort of not as, you
know, to make it clear that it was something different from normal
קיום שטרות. kiyum shtaros. So maybe for רבה, Rabbah, you don't even
have to be hearing them doing it לשמה, lishmah, right? That's why
should you have to? I mean, you know, if you so it's
just about בפני נכתב bifnei nichtav to set this aside as something
different from class קיום שטרות. kiyum shtaros. Anyway, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: אמר מר, amar mar, let's take a look
at what was just said. אפילו נכנס ויוצא כל היום כולו כשר,
afilu nichnas veyotzei kol hayom kulo kasher, even if you're going in
and out the whole day, it's kosher. מאן, Man, now who's going
in and out? אילימא שליח, ilima shliach, the guy who's going to
bring the גט get who has to testify? השתא הוא בבית והסופר
בעליה דלא חזי ליה, hashtas hu babayis vehasofer ba'aliya d'lo chazi lei,
if the סופר sofer is upstairs and you're downstairs and
you're not seeing it at all, you're just hearing some voices and
sharpening of the quills or whatever, but you're not even physically present,
אמרת כשר, amarta kasher, it's kosher. נכנס ויוצא מיבעיא, nichnas veyotzei miba'aya,
so how could you think that it would be any worse, it
should be פסול pasul if you're actually going in and out from
where the סופר sofer is physically present? Because in and out suggests
that it's from where the person is actually physically present. Okay, so
obviously that's okay, why would you have to tell me that case?
אלא סופר, ela sofer, so it means that the
סופר, sofer, you're both in the same room and the סופר sofer
is running out to go and, you know, to go do an
errand and then he comes back and even so you can
say בפני נכתב. bifnei nichtav. So the
גמרא Gemara says פשיטא, pshita, that's
obvious. משום דנכנס ויוצא מיפסל? mishum denichnas veyotzei mipasal? Do I think,
would I have reason to think that just because the סופר sofer
went in and out, it should be פסול? pasul? Why is that
what's the point of telling me that? לא צריכה, lo tzricha, you
need it for the following case. דנפיק לשוקא ואתא, d'nafik l'shuka ve'asa,
he didn't just go in and out, you know, to get a
breath of fresh air, he went actually out to the store. ואתא
מהו דתימא, ve'asa mahu d'seima, and then he came back, I might
have thought איניש אחרינא אשכחיה ואמר ליה, inish achrina ashkechei ve'amar lei,
maybe when he was out at the store, somebody else said to
him, you know, I have a more urgent גט get and I
need you to write it for my wife. And then when the
סופר sofer was coming back, he was writing it with this other
guy in mind, you know, there's all questions about if they all
have the same name, how would the גט get be כשר kasher
and so on, but anyway, but maybe that led to him to
distract him and he was no longer had the right לשמה lishmah
intent. קא משמע לן ka mashma lan that we're not concerned about
that. Okay, so here we are back to though an issue about
the לשמה, lishmah, but again that doesn't really say whether you have
to have evidence that it's being done לשמה. lishmah. That would more
be for
רבא, Rava, for רבה... Rabbah... Presumably the standard could be much lower
what's needed to be able to say בפני נכתב befanai nichtav if
we're not, if there's no real need to testify about the לשמה.
lishma. Okay, so that is a practical question about what the סופר
sofer needs. So now we've moving on from I mean רבה Rabbah
and רבא Rava always remains in the background but we're moving on
from trying to prove or disprove and point out the implications to
now talk about the different sort of criteria or the different circumstances
about how this בפני נכתב befanai nichtav plays out. So one is
what constitutes בפני נכתב, befanai nichtav, in terms of we already said
what is the,
what happens if the שליח shaliach gives it without having said it,
how can it be fixed, does he have to take it back,
does he have to give it before two or before three, who
can give it? We've referenced discussions later on about a woman or
the or the wife herself. Okay, and now we are talking about
the next thing is the places. The משנה Mishna discussed ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael and מדינת הים Medinat Hayam and it had a whole
question about border cities. And now we're going to discuss בבל, Bavel,
which was the main place in the time of the בבלי Bavli
and even a major place in the time of when the משנה
Mishna was being written, but certainly when the בבלי Bavli and ירושלמי,
Yerushalmi, when the גמרות Gemarot were being written, the mainstay of
the Jewish community, the majority of the Jewish population lived in בבל.
Bavel. So what is that status? So let's take a look. איתמר
Itmar was taught: בבל, Bavel, what's the status of בבל? Bavel? רב
אמר כארץ ישראל לגיטין. Rav amar k'Eretz Yisrael l'gittin. It's like ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael when it comes to a גט. get. Now we're
not talking about going from בבל Bavel to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
right, if there's a concern
about having witnesses able to confirm the signatures, that we have to
ask what the degree of travel is. We're talking about within בבל,
Bavel, right? Within בבל Bavel and presumably let's say first within the
question of
לשמה, lishma, so within ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, at least through the
לשמה lishma lens we know that's not a
problem from one place to another in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
And how about in בבל, Bavel, one place to another, what's the
לשמה lishma issue there? The other through the lens of עדים מצויים
לקיימו, edim metzuyim lekaymo, through the רבא Rava lens,
in
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, right, according to the way the גמרא Gemara
explained it before, because there's a lot of travel because of the
בתי דינים, batei dinim, even from one country to another in ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, like יהודה Yehuda to גליל Galil and so on,
there's not a, we're not concerned for need of establishing the signatures.
So is there a similar type of consideration in בבל? Bavel? So
with either lens, does בבל Bavel be similar to ארץ ישראל? Eretz
Yisrael? Okay, רב אמר כארץ ישראל לגיטין ושמואל אמר כחוצה לארץ. Rav
amar k'Eretz Yisrael l'gittin u'Shmuel amar k'chutza la'aretz. No, it's just like
חוצה לארץ. chutza la'aretz. לימא בהא קמיפלגי? Lima beha kamiflagi? Maybe this
is the debate. דמר סבר לפי שאין בקיאין לשמה, D'mar savar lefi
she'ein bekiyin lishma, and these are, one would say that it's a
לשמה lishma problem and there's no question that in בבל Bavel the
knowledge of תורה Torah and הלכה halakha was very, very high. ומר
סבר U'mar savar
and the other one holds לפי שאין עדים מצויים לקיימו, lefi she'ein
edim metzuyim lekaymo,
that the issue is about being able to have witnesses available to
validate the signatures. והני נמי לא שכיחי, V'hanei nami lo shechichi, so
from one מדינה medina to another מדינה medina in בבל, Bavel, that
also would not be,
there's not a lot of travel presumably and that would be like
any two מדינות medinot and therefore you would need to say בפני
נכתב. befanai nichtav. So רב Rav is taking the ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, says it's like ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael focused on לשמה lishma
and שמואל Shmuel says it's like חוצה לארץ chutza la'aretz focuses on
the need to validate the signatures. So that's reasonable, except the גמרא
Gemara says, as it's been saying, ותסברא? v'tisbara? Does that make sense
as a way of explaining the debate? הא רבה אית ליה דרבא.
Ha Rabbah it lei d'Rava. We've established that רבה Rabbah is also
concerned with רבא, Rava, is also concerned with עדים מצויים לקיימו. edim
metzuyim lekaymo. So everybody needs to address the issue
about is there going to be witnesses. So if there's a debate
about whether you need to say or not from one country to
another within בבל, Bavel, there must be a debate about how prevalent
the travel is and how great a degree there would be to
need to validate the witnesses now or could we assume that we'd
be able to do it when if and when needed. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this: אלא דכולי עלמא עדים מצויים
לקיימו. Ela d'kulei alma edim metzuyim lekaymo. Fine, you're right. Everybody is
focused on the לקיימו lekaymo and to the degree that there was
a לשמה lishma issue, it certainly is not a problem in בבל.
Bavel. רב סבר כיון דאיכא
בי
ספתי שכיחי. Rav savar keivan d'ika bei siftei mishcha sh'chichi. Since there
are ישיבות, yeshivot,
therefore there's always a lot of travel from one ישיבה yeshiva to
the
next. And now how do you know people are always traveling to
and from a ישיבה yeshiva town? But whatever, presumably an industry builds
up around all of the travel and the visiting and the moving
and maybe they meant specifically within the major, within,
that the basic different
מדינות medinot are the places in each one of them where there's
a major ישיבה. yeshiva. Okay, and if you take a look at
רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi points out that רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel
each had their own ישיבה. yeshiva. Well, actually let'll hold off that
רש"י Rashi a second. Okay, ושמואל סבר מסיפתי גירסייהו טרידי. U'Shmuel savar
misiftei girsaihu tridi. No, the ישיבות, yeshivot, the ישיבה בחורים yeshiva bachurim
are too busy learning. They're not like going into business and they're
and they're spending a lot of time in the shops and they're
watching people sign their signatures. So there might be a lot of
travel, but that does not mean that you can assume that people
will always be available who can testify to signatures. Okay, so that's
the issue. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. He says
about the ישיבה, Yeshiva, you know the ישיבה בחורים Yeshiva bachurim are
too busy learning. They're not like going into business and they're spending
a lot of time in the shops and they're watching people sign
their signatures. So there might be a lot of travel, but that
does not mean that you can assume that people will always be
available who can testify to signatures. Okay, so that's the issue. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. איתמר Itmar נמי nami was
also taught, אמר רבי אבא אמר רבא אמר רב הונא עשינו עצמנו
בבבל כארץ ישראל לגיטין. amar Rabbi Abba amar Rava amar Rav Huna
asinu atzmeinu be-Vavel ke-Eretz Yisrael le-gittin. So it said, we started treating
ourselves in בבל Bavel like ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael for גיטין... Gittin...
and where are we? איתמר Itmar נמי nami was also taught, אמר
רבי אבא אמר רבא אמר רב הונא עשינו עצמנו בבבל כארץ ישראל
לגיטין. amar Rabbi Abba amar Rava amar Rav Huna asinu atzmeinu be-Vavel
ke-Eretz Yisrael le-gittin. So it said, we started treating ourselves in בבל
Bavel like ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael for the matters of גט, get,
מכי אתא רב לבבל, mi-ki-asa Rav le-Vavel, from the time that רב
Rav arrived in בבל. Bavel. So the same רב ושמואל Rav u-Shmuel
that we were discussing who had this debate and רב Rav said
we're all like ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, now we find out that
that new
status was sort of recognized when רב Rav arrived. Why is it
significant when רב Rav arrived? So if you look at רש"י, Rashi,
רש"י Rashi says,
first במתיבתא, bi-mesivta, רש"י Rashi says ישיבות קבועות אחת בסורא ואחת בנהרדעא.
yeshivot kevuot achas be-Sura ve-achas be-Naharda'a. So when there are ישיבות, yeshivot,
there's one in סורא, Sura, one in נהרדעא, Naharda'a, the two major
population centers ושכיחי תלמידי מזו לזו ושאר עיירות להם ביומי תורה, ve-shakhen
talmidim mizu la-zu u-she'ar ayaros la-hem biyomei tora, and there's a lot
of movement from all the little villages they come to these centers
and from these centers they come from one center to the next.
So presumably there's just a lot of travel all over the place.
Alright, and then מכי אתא רב לבבל mi-ki-asa Rav le-Vavel says רש"י,
Rashi, הוה בנהרדעא, hava be-Naharda'a, okay I'm sorry, וקבע ישיבה בסורא ודשמואל
הוה בנהרדעא. ve-kava yeshiva be-Sura ve-de-Shmuel hava be-Naharda'a. So the רב ושמואל,
Rav u-Shmuel, the two major ישיבה yeshiva centers were of course the
cause of all this travel, that was רב ושמואל. Rav u-Shmuel. רב
Rav was in סורא Sura and שמואל Shmuel was in נהרדעא. Naharda'a.
Now רש"י Rashi makes an important statement which תוספות Tosafot sort of
disagrees about. Remember now the emphasis
is about the travel issue, not the לשמה lishma issue, that's our
focus now. So רש"י Rashi says why was רב Rav central to
coming to בבל, Bavel, why was that central to the whole degree
of enormous amount of travel that took place. So רש"י Rashi says
the following. He says אבל מעיקרא לא, aval me-ikara lo, originally there
was not these ישיבות yeshivot with all this travel. ואף אגב דגמירי
דמשגלה יכניה לבבל והחרש והמסגר עמו לא פסקה תורה מהם. ve-af agav
de-gemiri di-mishiga gali Yechanya le-Vavel ve-he-charash ve-ha-masger imo lo pesika tora me-hem.
It's true that from the very beginning of the settlement in בבל
Bavel after the first destruction of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, the
תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim came to בבל, Bavel, there was always a
lot of תורה tora in בבל. Bavel. הלל Hillel came from, who
was the major starter of the whole רבי יהודה הנשיא, Rabbi Yehuda
HaNasi, that whole leadership went all the way back to הלל, Hillel,
that was הלל Hillel came from בבל. Bavel.
But nevertheless that although there was always תורה, tora, we're not here
focusing on the תורה, tora, we're focusing here on the travel and
the whole institution of major ישיבה yeshiva centers in סורא ונהרדעא, Sura
ve-Naharda'a, that came with רב Rav and then with שמואל Shmuel and
therefore that's why we now treat ourselves like ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
Okay, so according to this now it seems like the status changed
and that's understandable. It used to be that there wasn't a lot
of travel, now there is a lot of travel within this region
so you no longer have to say it. Let's take a look
at where the גמרא Gemara goes with this.
He says like this. איתמר, Itmar, we just, okay, מתיב רבי ירמיה.
masiv Rabbi Yirmiya. רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya challenges this from our משנה.
mishna. רבי יהודה אומר מרקם למזרח ורקם כמזרח מאשקלון לדרום ואשקלון כדרום
מעכו לצפון ועכו כצפון, Rabbi Yehuda omer mi-Rekem la-mizrach ve-Rekem ke-mizrach mi-Ashkelon
la-darom ve-Ashkelon ke-darom mi-Akko la-tzafon ve-Akko ke-tzafon,
these are the outer edges of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael according to
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. רקם Rekem is on the east and רקם
Rekem itself is outside of ישראל, Yisrael, אשקלון Ashkelon is the south,
אשקלון Ashkelon south is considered outside for the laws of גיטין, gittin,
and עכו Akko is the north and עכו Akko is considered the
north itself outside. והבבל לצפונה דארץ ישראל קיימא, ve-ha-Bavel li-tzfona de-Eretz Yisrael
kayama, and we know בבל Bavel is to the north of ישראל
Yisrael דכתיב de-ksiv as it says ויאמר ה' אלי מצפון תפתח הרעה,
va-yomer Hashem elai mi-tzafon tipasach ha-ra'ah, the evil will come from the
north and that was the prophecy of בבל Bavel coming to destroy
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Of course how that exactly, what where
it exactly is on a map is sort of being bracketed, but
that's how we know through the פסוקים. psukim. Anyway it doesn't matter,
if the point is that every place outside of ישראל Yisrael to
the north and east and south are considered חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz,
that includes בבל. Bavel. So you see that בבל Bavel has the
same status as חוץ לארץ. chutz la'aretz. ותנן u-tnan and we taught
רבי מאיר אומר עכו כארץ ישראל לגיטין. Rabbi Meir omer Akko ke-Eretz
Yisrael le-gittin. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who said oh עכו, Akko, that's
going to be like ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. ואפילו רבי מאיר לא
קאמר אלא בעכו דמקרבא, ve-afillu Rabbi Meir lo kama ela be-Akko di-mikarva,
even רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir only said it by עכו Akko that's
like right there on the border, it's close. אבל בבל דמרחקא לא,
aval Bavel de-merachka lo, but by בבל Bavel he would not have
said that. So clearly everything outside of the borders of ישראל, Yisrael,
there might be a debate exactly where to draw the line, but
everything outside is חוץ לארץ. chutz la'aretz. How could you say בבל
Bavel has the status of ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? הוא מתיב לה
והוא מפרש לה. hu masiv lah ve-hu mifarsh lah. He asked it
and he answered it לבר מבבל. le-bar mi-Bavel. No, it means other
than בבל. Bavel. Like it's like everything else out there is חוץ
לארץ chutz la'aretz except of course the major center of בבל, Bavel,
that's a whole separate entity, we're not talking about that. Okay that
was clearly understood that you would not label בבל Bavel in its,
true, you know מדינת הים Medinas Hayam תוספות Tosafot says at the
very beginning. Why not say חוץ לארץ? chutz la'aretz? You know מדינת
הים Medinas Hayam has a specific type of an identity and בבל
Bavel is clearly a different identity. Now the issue with this of
course is that since the גמרא Gemara said that the status changed
when רב Rav came to בבל, Bavel, why is it that you
can ask from the משנה? mishna? The משנה mishna doesn't really prove
anything.
So there's one or two ways of understanding this. You could because
the משנה mishna was before רב Rav came to בבל, Bavel, so
obviously it's not in the משנה. mishna. So it could be, it
doesn't seem this way, but it could be that what the גמרא
Gemara is saying is is that since the משנה mishna is not
drawing any distinctions and the משנה mishna paints all of חוץ לארץ
chutz la'aretz in one brush, then even when the reality changes we're
not going to change something's status of חוץ לארץ. chutz la'aretz. You
know it's sort of like we saw before כדי שלא תחלוק במדינת
הים, kedei she-lo tachalok bi-Medinas Hayam, רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer position. Alright,
and then the גמרא Gemara Is no, like you know, maybe we
could exclude a whole area that is, you know, even if we
painted all of חוץ לארץ Chutz la'Aretz one way, if there's a
whole new region that has its own identity, it's not like a
small little situation, right, that would be different. It doesn't sound that
way. So because of that, תוספות Tosafot redefines what the earlier statement
meant of when רב Rav came to בבל. Bavel. If you look
at תוספות, Tosafot, מכי אתא רב לבבל, mechi ata Rav l'Bavel, תוספות
Tosafot says פירוש הקונטרס perush hakuntres והרבה ישיבות, v'hirba yeshivot, and רב
Rav was the one who instituted many yeshivas. וקשיא דאם כן מאי
פרך ממשנתינו v'kashya d'im ken mai parach mimisnaseinu דמאקלו צפון dem'Aklo tsafon
שניתנה קודם לביאת רב לבבל. she'nitna kodem l'vi'at Rav l'Bavel. So if
that's true, that it was a change of status, why does the
גמרא Gemara think that there was a change, why does it think
it can challenge it from the משנה? Mishnah? ומפרש רבינו תם u'mefaresh
Rabbeinu Tam מכי אתא רב לבבל mechi ata Rav l'Bavel והורה לנו
שמוסד יכניה שגלו עמו לבבל החרש והמסגר דינו להיות כארץ ישראל לגיטין.
v'hora lanu she'mosad Yechanya she'galu imo l'Bavel he'charash v'hamasger dino l'hiyot k'Eretz
Yisrael l'Gittin. So when רב Rav came to בבל, Bavel, he taught
us this הלכה. halacha. It wasn't the change in society that רב
Rav brought with him, it was רב Rav just taught us this
הלכה. halacha. I mean, the גמרא Gemara sounds a lot more like
רש״י, Rashi, and we should point out that even according to
תוספות, Tosafot, you know, the point still is is that why would
we have to, I mean, maybe the גמרא Gemara just thought it,
but like, why would it be important to say that he told
us this always was the case? Because to some degree, we want
things to fit in with the משנה. Mishnah. We don't want to
have to assert change of status. So one way or the other,
whether it actually was a status change or we're saying it always
was there, it's not in contradiction to the משנה Mishnah because the
משנה Mishnah can allow for this type of an exception. Okay. עד
היכן היא בבל? ad heichan hi Bavel? How far is בבל? Bavel?
What are the actual parameters of בבל? Bavel? Now that it's going
to matter להלכה. l'halacha. אמר
רב פפא כמחלוקת ליוחסין כך מחלוקת לגיטין.
Amar Rav Papa
k'machloket l'yuchasin kach machloket l'Gittin. There's a debate by יוחסין yuchasin in
קידושין Kiddushin about like when are people, you know, you know, just
whatever how certain we can be assumed about people's personal status. And
the best place is בבל. Bavel. בבל's Bavel people's personal status is
like most assured, interestingly even more than ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. And
there's a discussion there, what are the, what are the boundaries of
בבל? Bavel? So whatever that debate is here, it would apply here.
Okay. Now again, does this reflect, because remember the considerations are different,
right? One place is a question about, this is sort of an
ongoing thing about this first פרק. perek. One place the question is
about
like where do people know their personal status, where have records been
kept and so on. And in the other situation, by יוחסין, yuchasin,
it's a question about like where is there a lot of travel
from place to place so you don't have to worry about signatures
and so on, or you know, about validating now, you won't have
to worry about it later. So
and, so does it really happen that those two exactly overlap? Or
is the point that you know what, like we can't have a
million different definitions and therefore we're going to adopt, you know, standard
definitions and use them even if they don't exactly fit? You know,
we've seen that כדי שלא תחלוק במדינת הים, kedei shelo tachlok b'medinat
hayam, we're going to continue to see those types of things. Okay.
Anyway, that's what he says. כך מחלוקת לגיטין. kach machloket l'Gittin. ורב
יוסף אמר מחלוקת ליוחסין. v'Rav Yosef amar machloket l'yuchasin. No, no, no.
That debate over there by יוחסין, yuchasin, it's that debate. אבל לגיטין,
aval l'Gittin, when it comes to גיטין, Gittin, דברי הכל, divrei hakol,
everybody agrees עד ערבא תיניינא דגשרא, ad arba tinyana d'gashra, until the
second arch of the, you know, of the bridge. So there was
clearly the גמרא Gemara knew what that was referring to, and
and you know, and like which bridge, which arch, you know, that's
only one direction, what about the other directions? But anyway, for that
the גמרא Gemara understood that was the boundary in terms of these
issues.
Okay. Now we have a case. רב
חסדא מצריך מאקטיספון לבי ארדשיר. Rav Chisda matzrich m'Aktisphon l'Bei Ardashir. רב
חסדא Rav Chisda required that if somebody is going from אקטיספון Aktisphon
to בי ארדשיר, Bei Ardashir, they had to say בפני נכתב. b'fanai
nichtav.
ומבי ארדשיר לאקטיספון לא מצריך. u'miBei Ardashir l'Aktisphon lo matzrich. And from
the, in the opposite direction they did not. Okay, so not exactly
clear like is one in בבל Bavel and one in חוץ לארץ,
Chutz la'Aretz, are they both in בבל? Bavel? תוספות Tosafot starts to
trigger it all out, but anyway we can get the gist even
without sort of completely, you know, getting into all that. Okay, so
let's take a look. ומבי ארדשיר לאקטיספון לא מצריך. u'miBei Ardashir l'Aktisphon
lo matzrich. לימא קסבר לפי שאין בקיאין לשמה ואינהו בקיאי. Leima kasavar
l'fi she'ein beki'in lishmah v'inhu beki'ei. Okay.
So the best way to explain why you needed it in one
direction and not the other is like it sort of, you know,
it echoes ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and מדינת הים, medinat hayam, that
in one place they know לשמה, lishmah, and in the other place
they don't. So presumably if you have to say it from אקטיספון,
Aktisphon, when you're going from אקטיספון Aktisphon to בי ארדשיר, Bei Ardashir,
that's because אקטיספון Aktisphon doesn't know לשמה, lishmah, so therefore בי ארדשיר's
Bei Ardashir going to insist that they hear them say בפני נכתב.
b'fanai nichtav. Whereas in the reverse, בי ארדשיר Bei Ardashir knows לשמה
lishmah and they don't have to say בפני נכתב. b'fanai nichtav. Okay,
that would be if your only concern were לשמה lishmah and there
were no travel concerns. Okay. But as we, okay, so let's take
a look. So the גמרא Gemara says לימא... leima... ומבי ארדשיר לאקטיספון
לא מצריך. u'miBei Ardashir l'Aktisphon lo matzrich. לימא... leima... ורבא אית ליה
דרבה. v'Rava it lei d'Rabba.
So many times we have a nice way of explaining things that
it's about לשמה, lishmah, but then the גמרא Gemara does not, it
can't go forward because other sources pushed us to say that רבא
Rava agrees to רבה. Rabba. That there's always a question about the
travel. Okay now, you could maybe just say that there's a lot
of travel between the two places and there's still לשמה lishmah difference.
But for some reason, the גמרא Gemara doesn't go that way. So
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says
or the way רש״י Rashi says it. ורבא אית ליה דרבה וכיון
דמדינא למדינא הוא בעינן לקיומיה. v'Rava it lei d'Rabba v'keivan d'medina l'medina
hu ba'inan l'kiyumei. רש״י Rashi says, you know, we have to since
these are clearly two different מדינות, medinot, therefore you should require it
in both cases. But Again, you could address that by saying there’s
a lot of travel and still focus on the לשמה lishma difference,
but the גמרא Gemara doesn’t do that. Here’s what the גמרא Gemara
does: איבעית
אימא דרבא אלא דכולי עלמא בעינן לקיימו.
Iba’it eima de’Rava
ella dechulei alma ba’inan lekaymo. You’re right. Everybody agrees about the need
to do קיום. kiyyum. והני ביני והני כי מיזלי בשוקא להתם הנך
ידעי בחתימת ידי דהני. vahani be’inei vahani kimeizali beshuka lehaseim hanach yadei
bechasimeit yadei dehani. So but these because they go to the שוק,
shuk, the marketplace of there, since A goes to marketplace of B,
so everybody in B knows the signatures. Why? Because A is the
transient population. They come in, they go out and they buy things,
they sign IOUs, they sign documents, okay, and then they go home,
and then B-town is left with all these signed documents. So they
have an opportunity to sort of become more familiar with who is
signing what documents. You know, it seems like, you know, it’s interesting
right? Because since town B is selling and town A is buying,
town A might, you know, and you’re buying, if you’re buying real
estate, it might be different, the seller would have to sign the
document, but if you’re buying, you know, movables, then the only then
town A wants to, like, is going to sign checks, is going
to, you know, sign IOUs, and so on. Okay, so therefore town
B knows the signatures of town ה hey of town A. והני
בהנך לא ידעי, vahani behanach lo yadei, but the reverse is not
true. In town A wouldn’t know the signatures of town B. And
that’s why, מאי טעמא בשוקאי טרידי. mai ta’ama beshuka’i teridei. They’re busy
with their buying and selling. Now, town A is also doing the
buying and selling, but as רש״י Rashi sort of says, it’s not
they’re yeah, but town A then but town A after their buying
and selling goes back home. Town B is left with all the
signed documents. Okay.
רב בר אבוה מצריך מרסתא לרסתא. Rav bar Avuha matzrich merasta lerasta.
רב בר אבוה Rav bar Avuha required even going from like one
row of houses, you know, one side
of a רשות הרבים reshous harabim to another row of houses on
another side of a רשות הרבים. reshous harabim. Why? Because we’ll see
in a minute because there’s a transient population and therefore the thing
the feeling was this is the way תוספות Tosafos explains it very
clearly that let’s say, you know, you have people in this both
sides of the street or whatever, you know, there are people there
that know signatures of other people. So this person this opinion said
if there are people on my side of the street, you know,
a husband is giving a גט get to his wife and everybody
lives on my side of this major thoroughfare, okay, and I know
that there are people who know and the witnesses signed it and
they’re all coming from this section, then
then I don’t have to do קיום, kiyyum, I don’t have to
בפני נכתב. bifanei nechtav. Why? Because if I I hear what’s going
on in this section of of my town. So therefore, you know,
it’s like the other side of the tracks, right? So you know,
different sides. So therefore, if the people, the witnesses who know who
who signed it or who know these signatures, people, you know, are
going to move, I the wife, you know, or the people who
care for the wife, are going to find out before it happens
and make sure to do קיום. kiyyum. But if they’re going to
move from the other side of the track, if the גט get
came from the other side of the tracks and that’s where the
witnesses were and the people that know the witnesses’ signatures, then I
the wife won’t be like know if they’re about to, you know,
it’s a transient population, if they’re going to move and then I’m
not going to be able to do קיום. kiyyum. So in that
case, even though we’re physically very close, because it’s a transient population
and you’re only aware when the people closest to you are moving,
you would if when they come from a little bit like other
side of the track, that’s when you would have to do בפני
נכתב bifanei nechtav so you don’t get stuck without the ability to
do קיום. kiyyum. Okay.
So that’s what he says. Where are we?
Okay. רב ששת מצריך משכונה לשכונה. Rav Sheshes matzrich mishchuna leshchuna. רב
ששת Rav Sheshes required no, even on the same side of the
tracks from like one neighborhood to the other, that even on even
if they’re all in that same region, if you’re in a different
neighborhood and רש״י Rashi says even three houses, but I assume means
that there’s something that distinguishes them. Anyway, if you’re in a different
neighborhood that therefore the you know, you need to do בפני נכתב
bifanei nechtav because you are afraid that you will not be able
to get the witnesses when you need
them, they’ll leave and you won’t have known that they’ve moved.
ורבא מצריך באותה שכונה. veRava matzrich be’osa shechuna. And רבא Rava required
even like somebody like within your neighborhood. You know, there’s so much
transience and nobody knows who’s going and who’s coming and therefore you’re
always at risk and therefore you always have to do בפני נכתב
בפני נכתב. bifanei nechtav bifanei nechtav. ורבא הוא דאמר לפי שאין עדים
מצויין לקיימו. veRava hu de’amar lefi she’ein eidin metzuyim lekaymo. Now I
already gave it away a little bit, but the גמרא Gemara says
wait one minute, I don’t get it. רבא Rava says it’s a
problem about עדים. eidin. So what what’s the issue here about one
שכונה? shechuna? I mean, if it were לשמה, lishma, I mean wouldn’t
have explained the differences before between side of the tracks and neighborhood
about לשמה, lishma, but at least we would have understood that if
it’s like even if it’s next door, if it’s a problem about
לשמה, lishma, that could explain why you would always need it. So
at least an extreme position of even somebody next door you have
to do it makes sense לשמה. lishma. But what sense does it
make if it’s about being able to do קיום? kiyyum? So the
גמרא Gemara says no, שאני בני מחוזא דניידי. shani benei Mechuza de’naidi.
רבא Rava was from מחוזא. Mechuza. בני מחוזא benei Mechuza was very
transient population and was like a metropolis or certainly cosmopolitan. Anyway and
therefore he required it and that’s why even next door and that
explains certainly the earlier positions that make a distinction between this neighborhood
and the other neighborhood. Take a look at תוספות. Tosafos. What sense
does it make if it's about being able to do קיום? kiyum?
So the גמרא Gemara says no, שאני בני מחוזא דניידי. Shani b'nei
Mechuza d'naidi. רבא Rava was from מחוזא. Mechuza. בני מחוזא B'nei Mechuza
was very transient population, was like a metropolis, or certainly cosmopolitan, anyway,
and therefore he required it, and that's why even next door and
that explains certainly the earlier positions that make a distinction between this
neighborhood and the other neighborhood. If you take a look at תוספות,
Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says שאני בני מחוזא דניידי. Shani b'nei Mechuza d'naidi.
מכאן פוסק רבינו תם דהשתא בזמן הזה צריך לומר בכל מקום בפני
נכתב ובפני נחתם Mikan posek Rabbeinu Tam d'hashta bizman hazeh tzarich lomar
b'chol makom b'fanay nechtav u'v'fanay nechtam אף על גב דקיימא לן כרבא
af al gav d'kayma lan k'Rava דאמר לפי שאין בקיאין לקיימו d'amar
lefi she'ain b'ki'in l'kaymo even though we hold like רבא Rava that
אין בקיאין לקיימו. ain b'ki'in l'kaymo. And even though somebody might have
said, you know, that they know לשמה lishmah in the places in
where the בעלי התוספות Ba'alei haTosafot lived, you know, very learned population
by and large. Anyway, ולא משום לשמה, v'lo mishum lishmah, מכל מקום,
micol makom, but we don't even have to discuss לשמה, lishmah, it's
about מצויים. metzuyim. Nevertheless,
even if you're in the same place, you always have to say
בפני נחתם, b'fanay nechtam, why? צריך דהשתא בכל מקומות ניידי כבני מחוזא
tzarich d'hashta b'chol makomos naidi k'b'nei Mechuza because we are a very
transient population which we know was true about the, you know, time
of the medieval period, you know, and the ראשונים Rishonim and so
on. So the interesting thing about all of this, well first of
all I should say that even if you פסק paskened you didn't
have to, if you said it, it works, and that's important and
that was the earlier גמרא, Gemara, and that really protects the woman
in saying and if it ever does get challenged. But the interesting
thing about this is the way things again, this question about are
things static from the time they were in the משנה, Mishnah, right?
Did the גמרא Gemara want to, you know, תוספות, Tosafot, you know,
was the גמרא Gemara willing to think that the status of בבל
Bavel changed since the time of the משנה Mishnah or not? And
here, you know, the status of the הלכה halacha of the same
מדינה medinah in חוץ לארץ Chutz l'Aretz requires, that has been overridden
by this idea of transient populations. Now you could say that, you
know, exceptions were already being carved out, הגמוניא לאגמוניא מקפידין זה על
זה Hagmonya l'Agmonya makpidin zeh al zeh and so on, but nevertheless,
it is interesting how much how this is being changing from the
time of the משנה. Mishnah. Okay,
moving on. רב חנין
משתעי. Rav Hanin mishtai. רב חנין Rav Hanin sort of indicated, you
know, gestured, whatever, related. רב כהנא אייתי גיטא. Rav Kahana ayiti gita.
רב כהנא Rav Kahana brought a גט. get. ולא ידענא אם מסורא
לנהרדעא אם מנהרדעא לסורא, v'lo yadana im miSura l'Nehardea im miNehardea l'Sura,
I don't know if it was from סורא Sura to נהרדעא Nehardea
or נהרדעא Nehardea to סורא, Sura, right? Those were the two places
of a lot of travel. אתא לקמיה דרב, ata l'kamei d'Rav, he
came before רב. Rav. אמר ליה צריכינא למימר בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם
או לא צריכינא? amar lei tzrichina l'meimar b'fanay nechtav u'v'fanay nechtam o
lo tzrichina? Do I have to say בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם b'fanay
nechtav u'v'fanay nechtam or do I not? אמר ליה לא צריכת, amar
lei lo tzarichat, you don't have to because like we said before
that בבל Bavel is like ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and there's a
lot of travel, you don't have to say it. Top of ו'
עמוד ב'. vav amud bet. ואי עבד מהני, v'ee avad mahni, and
if you did it it worked, okay? So
actually I think I just said this a second ago.
Right, so anyway. Okay, I think I said it was before but
here it is now. מאי ואי עבד מהני? mai v'ee avad mahni?
What does it mean that if you did it it worked? דאי
אתי בעל מערער לא משכחינן ביה, d'ee ayta ba'al m'ar'er lo mishkachinan
beh, that you will now protect the woman. So even in a
case where you don't have to, which is the case of בבל,
Bavel, you know what? If you're able to say it, you might
as well say it because it'll protect the woman and if the
בעל ba'al comes and complains we won't pay attention to him. Now
going way back, you know, this debate of רש"י Rashi and תוספות.
Tosafot. רש"י Rashi said that even if the husband were to say
it,
you know, even like, you know, before the חובת בפני נכתב chovat
b'fanay nechtav got established and so on,
that or you know if the שליח shaliach didn't say בפני נכתב
b'fanay nechtav we don't פוסק pasken like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Anyway,
you know, if the בעל ba'al doesn't if the בעל ba'al says
it, it's just a לעז, la'az, the only thing we were concerned
about was a לעז. la'az. The בעל ba'al never really had the
power to invalidate. So בפני נכתב b'fanay nechtav though creates a structure
in which nobody will pay attention to the בעל. ba'al. But even
before that, you know, structure, the בעל ba'al never would have technically
validated. Alright, there's another way to read it, if you take a
look at רש"י. Rashi. אבל בלאו הכי ואתי בעל מערער מפסיל. aval
b'lav hachi v'ayti ba'al m'ar'er mefsil. רש"י Rashi says if you don't
say it and the בעל ba'al comes and he says it, he
will actually will invalidate. So there's an important debate of רש"י Rashi
and תוספות Tosafot in a case where you don't need to say
it, if the husband's challenging it will actually manage to invalidate it
or not.
Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, so now so there, you don't have to say it, but
if you do it'll protect the woman
and according to רש"י Rashi from actually invalidating the גט get and
according to תוספות Tosafot at least from rumors and so on. Okay,
we'll put down those rumors. כדתניא מעשה באדם אחד שהביא גט לפני
רבי ישמעאל. k'detanya ma'aseh b'adam echad sheheivi get lifnai Rabbi Yishmael. A
person brought a גט get to רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. אמר לו
צריך אני לומר בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם או איני צריך? amar lo
tzarich ani lomar b'fanay nechtav u'v'fanay nechtam o eini tzarich? Do I
have to say בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם b'fanay nechtav u'v'fanay nechtam or
do I not have to say? אמר לו בני מהיכן אתה? amar
lo b'ni me'heichan atah? Where are you from? אמר לו רבי מכפר
סיסאי אני. amar lo rabbi miKfar Sisai ani. I'm from כפר סיסאי.
Kfar Sisai. Okay. אמר לו צריך אתה לומר בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם
שלא תזקק לעדים. amar lo tzarich atah lomar b'fanay nechtav u'v'fanay nechtam
shelo tizakak l'edim. You have to say it in order that you
should not she should save her from having to need עדים edim
in the first place, which was like weird
and as we'll let's see how the גמרא Gemara sort of elaborates
this. לאחר שיצא נכנס לפניו רבי אלעאי. le'achar she'yatzah nichnas l'fanav Rabbi
Ilai. After he after this שליח shaliach went, רבי אלעאי Rabbi Ilai
came to him. אמר לו רבי והלא כפר סיסאי מובלע בתחום ארץ
ישראל וקרוב לציפורי יותר מעכו? amar lo rabbi v'halo Kfar Sisai muvla
b'tchum Eretz Yisrael v'karov l'Tzipori yoter me'Akko? Isn't isn't כפר סיסאי Kfar
Sisai a you know
like swallowed up within the borders of ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? Technically
it's on the line but it's sort of you know within like
there's ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael all around it and it's even closer
to ציפורי Tzipori more than עכו, Akko, and ציפורי Tzipori was like
a central location. If there was concerns about travel or לשמה. lishmah.
ותנן רבי מאיר אומר עכו כארץ ישראל לגיטין. u'tnan Rabbi Meir omer
Akko k'Eretz Yisrael l'gittin. עכו Akko is like ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
for גיטין. gittin. ואפילו רבנן לא פליגי עליה דרבי מאיר אלא בעכו.
v'afilu rabanan lo pligi alei d'Rabbi Meir ela b'Akko. Even the rabbis
only disagree about עכו Akko because it's so distant דמרחקא היא. d'merachka
hi. אבל כפר סיסאי דמקרבא לא. aval Kfar Sisai d'mekarva lo. But
כפר סיסאי Kfar Sisai that's close they would agree. It's funny that
they're pointing at that debate since, you know, that would seem to
be the issue of
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer in
the
משנה. Mishnah. So אמר ליה amrei lei so he said back to
him, שתוק בני שתוק, shtok bni shtok, quiet my son, hush hush
hush. הואיל ויצא דבר בהיתר יצא. ho-il v'yatza davar b'heter yatza. Since
it was פסקנד paskened that it's היתר, heter, meaning the היתר heter
is at the בפני נכתב befanei nechtav is effective, you know, it's
good, it takes effect. All right. Meaning, yes, you didn't have to
say it, but by saying it now, she was protected. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says: האי איהו נמי שלא לאידזק לעדים קאמר ליה?
Hai ihu nami shelo l'idizak l'eidim kamar lei? So why was Rebbe
Elai upset, you know, when when the ruling was originally given by
Rebbe Shmuel, Rebbe Shmuel said: Say it so she won't need עדים.
eidim. Not say it because halakhically the חזל Chazal have required you
to say it in this situation. But say it, you know, even
though again, this was not so clear. You have to say it
so she won't need עדים. eidim. But, you know, it was an
ambiguous statement. But the גמרא's Gemara's understanding that the second part is
saying you should say it in order to protect her from the
need of עדים; eidim; technically you don't have to but you should.
So this is the idea that even when you don't have to,
if you say it it works. So since he said that in
order to protect her, why was Rebbe Elai challenging him? So the
גמרא Gemara says: לא סיים קמיה. Lo siyem kamei. You know, it
was not finished in front of Rebbe Elai. Rebbe Elai did not
hear the end of, you know,
the end of what Rebbe Shmuel had said. He only, you know,
he reacted too soon without hearing the end and therefore he thought
that Rebbe Shmuel was saying it was real it genuinely was required.
Okay. שלח ליה רב אביתר לרב חסדא. Shelach lei Rav Avyasar l'Rav
Chisda. Rav Avyasar sent the following message to Rav Chisda: גיטין הבאים
משם לכאן. Gittin habaim misham l'kan. גיטין Gittin that come from there,
you in בבל Bavel to here, ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, אין צריך
לומר בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם. ein tzarich lomar befanei nechtav u'befanei nechtam.
Do not have to say בפני נכתב בפני נחתם. befanei nechtav befanei
nechtam. Now we're getting to the question about not within בבל Bavel
and within ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, but between בבל Bavel and ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Those are two מדינות, medinot, right? If there's an
issue about, you know, the גמרא Gemara said, you know, if there's
an issue about עדים שכיחי לקיים, eidim shchichi l'kayma, we know have
no evidence that from outside of Israel to inside Israel and vice
versa should not be a concern about בפני נכתב befanei nechtav because
of עדים. eidim. So let's take a look.
So he says they don't have to say it. למימרא דקסבר לריש
בקיום שמא ואני גמיראי? Leima kasavar l'rish b'kiyim shema v'ani gmirai? Let's
say he's not concerned about עדים, eidim, he's only concerned about לשמה
lishma and both בבל Bavel and ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael know about
לשמה. lishma. So the גמרא Gemara says: ותסברא, V'tisbra, does that make
sense? For רבה אית ליה דרבה Rabba it lei d'Rabba once again,
Rabba holds of Rabba. We always have to address the עדים eidim
issue. So who cares about לשמה? lishma? Or לשמה lishma isn't enough.
How do you deal with the issue about being able to know
signatures? אלא דכולי עלמא בעינן לקיים. Ela d'kuhlei alma b'inu l'kaymai. You're
right. You have to address the issue of the ability to be
מקיים mikayem the signatures.
וכיון דאיכא רבים דסלקי ונחתי, Vekivan d'ika rabim d'salki v'nechti, but since
there are a lot that סלקי salki go up ונחתי v'nechti and
go down, make עליה aliyah and ירידה, yerida, since there are a
lot of people that go from בבל Bavel to ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael and from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to בבל Bavel for, you
know, mostly around learning, but maybe also in general. Okay. So therefore
משכח שכיחי, mishkach shchichi, therefore there are always, you know, people there's
so much travel that it's not a problem, you know, you'll be
able to eventually find somebody that can do the that can be
מקיים mikayem the שטר. shtar. You know, one also wonders like does
it mean by chance? Or like maybe you could send a message
back that we need somebody, you know, or whatever. But with a
lot of travel we can sort of solve it and therefore same
within ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and within בבל, Bavel, also between ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael and between בבל. Bavel. Okay. משכח
שכיחי. mishkach shchichi. אמר רב יוסף, amar Rav Yosef, מאן לימא לן
דרב אביתר בר סמכא הוא? man lima lan d'Rav Avyasar bar Samcha
hu? Who said to you that you could rely on Rav Avyasar?
Now, you know, because he's coming with a קולא, kula, you don't
have to say בפני נכתב בפני נחתם. befanei nechtav befanei nechtam. Who
said you can rely on him? ועוד, Ve'od, and in addition, האי
איהו דשלח ליה, hai ihu d'shelach lei, now we're going to say
that he evidence that he did something that was seen as inappropriate.
There's an interesting question whether you have this word ועוד, ve'od, right?
Do you just in general say like, bah, who ever said you
could trust him? Or is there a particular thing? No, no, no,
we're not going to סתם stam say whoever said you could trust
him, you know, anyway let's weigh his statement and see if it
makes sense. But, you know, but we're going to challenge it because
we have a reason to challenge it. Who said you could trust
Rav Avyasar? האי איהו דשלח ליה, hai ihu d'shelach lei, see how
the statement reads differently when you take out the ועוד. ve'od. Who
said you could trust Rav Avyasar? האי איהו דשלח ליה, hai ihu
d'shelach lei, he sent to רב יהודה דרב יהודה Rav Yehuda d'Rav
Yehuda the following statement, okay. So, he sends a lot of missives
apparently from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to בבל. Bavel. Okay.
בני, Bni, בני אדם העולים משם לכאן, bnei adam haolim misham l'kan,
the people that are making עליה aliyah from בבל Bavel to ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, people that are coming here to learn תורה, Torah,
הם קיימו בעצמם ויתנו הילד בזונה והילדה מכרו ביין וישתו. heim kiyemu
b'atzman va'yitnu ha'yeled bazonah v'hayalda machru bayayin v'yishtu. They fulfilled on themselves
"they gave the child over to prostitution and the young girl they
sold for wine and they drank." Okay. Meaning so that they basically
they are you know like now what does he mean that's a
horrific verse. But what it means is is that there was a
lot of, you know, they left a lot of תורה Torah scholars
left בבל Bavel to go and spend many years in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael and they did not really do their responsibilities, you know,
financial responsibilities, providing for and just being present and and husbandly and
fatherly responsibilities. to their families back in בבל *Bavel* and therefore רב
אביתר *Rav Avyasar* here in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* was actually very
condemning of this practice and he said they have basically like you
know sold off their kids in order to allow themselves to learn
תורה *Torah* and you know you justify it because it's learning תורה
*Torah* but he was not prepared to justify. Now the word זונה
*zona* by the way
prostitution you know is very harsh but it can be read here
as the word as we'll see in a minute similarly as the
word מזונות *mezonot*. Take a look at תוספות *Tosafot* וינאטו הילד בזונה
*vayinaatu hayeled bazona* לפי שהם משתהים בארץ ישראל *lefi shehem mishta'aim beEretz
Yisrael* because they would spend a lot of time in Israel היו
בניהם ובנותיהם משתעבדים בשביל מזונות *hayu bneihem u'vnoteihem mishta'abdim bishvil mezonot* okay
they would have to their kids would have to go out and
provide for the family for food. וינאטו בזונה בשביל מזונות *vayinaatu bazona
bishvil mezonot* okay ועוד *va'od* and now here's an even harsher read.
מפרש קרא מהמפרשים קרא בירושלמי עובדא הוה בחד דמכר בתו ללמוד תורה
והלך ולמד *mefarsh kara mehamefarshim kara b'Yerushalmi uvda hava b'chad d'machar bito
lilmod Torah vehalach v'lamad*. He sold his daughter to go learn תורה
*Torah* as a you know as a slave okay so that's not
again technically זנות *znut* but it's literally sale and you know and
and whatever and you know those things can lead to improprieties. Okay
and רש''י *Rashi* by the way also important to read רש''י *Rashi*
וינאטו הילד *vayinaatu hayeled* רש''י *Rashi* says שהיו משתהים בארצות אחרות ומניחין
נשותיהן עגונות *shehayu mishta'aim b'aratzot acherot u'manichin n'shoteihen agunot* their wives עגונות
*agunot* meaning not like they were refusing a divorce but they were
leaving them abandoned and chained to their husbands ובטלים מפריה ורביה *u'vtelim
mipriyah u'reviyah* and they were not having the children they were supposed
to have שניכר ביניהם ילדים וילדות *shenikar beineihem yeladim v'yeladot* they didn't
care about having kids you know they it was more important them
to learn תורה *Torah*. So actually רש''י *Rashi* is a little interesting
not that they had kids and that they weren't providing for them
or maybe both are true but they weren't even having the kids
they were supposed to be having. So he wrote this very highly
critique you know critical thing and והכתיב ליה בלא
שירטוט *v'hichtiv lei b'lo sirtut* but we're going to focus on שירטוט
*sirtut*. He wrote it without scoring the קלף *klaf* you know scoring
the קלף *klaf* like writing a like doing like a an indent
you know with a sharp thing in the קלף *klaf* in order
that the that you can write the words in a straight line.
You know normally we imagine lines under like lined paper except this
was lined you know with a groove
but you know in the Hebrew writings part of the way it's
written in a ספר תורה *Sefer Torah* the line is above the
letters because there's things that go like above the line you know
all the tops of the letters have the same top line you
know but some things go below a bottom and some things go
above a top. Anyway he wrote it without scoring the קלף *klaf*
ורב יצחק *v'Rav Yitzchak* and רב
יצחק *Rav Yitzchak* teaches שתים כותבין *shtayim kotvin* if you want to
write two words from a פסוק *pasuk* you can write it without
scoring the קלף *klaf* שלש אין כותבין *shalosh ein kotvin* but not
three. מתניתא תנא *matnita tana* in a ברייתא *braita* we taught שלש
כותבין ארבע אין כותבין *shalosh kotvin arba ein kotvin* three you can
write without scoring four you can't. So look he went ahead and
he wrote this whole critique and you know maybe way also a
little blunting the critique but whatever he said ah who anyway what
does he know he doesn't even score the קלף *klaf*. So once
he did that now you can't go ahead and trust him you
know about this other thing like you know one was a real
critique the other was just a פסק *psak* oh because there's so
much travel you don't have to say פני נכתב *panai nichtav*. Anyway
but either way he's responding to this phenomenon but he says who
says you can trust him he doesn't even keep this basic הלכה
*halacha*. אמר ליה אביי *amar lei Abaye* אביי *Abaye* said אטו כולי
עלמא לא ידעי הא דרב יצחק לאו גברא רבא הוא *atu kuli
alma lo yad'ei ha d'Rav Yitzchak lav gavra raba hu* if you
don't know this position of רב יצחק *Rav Yitzchak* does that mean
that you're not a major authority that you don't need to even
score the קלף *klaf*. בשלמא מילתא דתליא בסברא לחיי *bishlama milta d'talya
b'savra lechai* if he had something that's dependent on like logic and
reasoning and he had like and he didn't think clearly then I
would agree with you okay you know if he's not somebody that
you can trust אבל הא גמרא גמרא היא *aval ha gmara gmara
hi* but this is a tradition וגמרא לא שמיע ליה *u'gmara lo
shmi'a lei* it was a tradition that רב יצחק *Rav Yitzchak* had
it some ברייתא *braita* not necessarily a well-known tradition. You know in
before the age of printed books and before the age of Bar
Ilan and computer and ספריה *Sefaria* and all of that it was
okay you know you didn't expect everybody to know every single tradition
that was out there.
אוקיי ועוד *okay va'od* so we're actually going to end here end
here for now and we will pick up with this tomorrow.